PROFESSOR: Today we're going to talk
about how reinforcement learning works
for more substantial problems.
Let's remind ourselves what's going
on in reinforcement learning.
In reinforcement learning, we
imagine that the world is a
Markov decision process.
Was does that mean?
It means there's a set of states, and
we can observe what state we're in.
It means there's a set of actions
that we can take.
And in a given state, we know
what actions we can take.
We imagine that each action has some
non-deterministic result, so there's
some transition function that, for a
given state in action, tells me what
can happen and with what probability.
The problem is I don't actually
know the transition function.
There's also a reward function-- that
for any given transition, meaning I
was in state S, I took action
A, and I landed in S prime.
There's some reward, which
we also don't know.
In reinforcement learning, we're
looking for a policy.
In particular, we're looking
for an optimal policy.
And the problem is, unlike for a known
MDP, we don't know the transitions or
the rewards until we experience them.
So how's this going to work?
Well, because we don't know what the
actions do, we actually have to try
various things out.
And that's going to commit us to a
certain amount of trial and error,
because there's just no way to know how
to act until you've experimented.
The big idea for reinforcement learning,
for solving these problems
and learning to act optimally, is to
look back to the things we used to do
with Markov decision processes when
we knew the transition function.
And everywhere where we have an average
over the outcomes, which in
order to compute requires knowing the
transition probabilities, T, we're
going to instead approximate those
with samples of outcomes.
So everywhere we saw an average over T,
we're going to try to find a way to
change our algorithm to compute that
average with samples rather than known
probabilities.
By now, you've seen a lot of things
that qualify as Bellman equations,
equations that relate the value at one
state to the value one state later,
after one action.
You've seen Q values in
terms of Q values.
You've seen values in
Some things had pi's, some
things had stars.
By now, you're probably in Bellman
equation overload.
All these things, when you aren't
used to them, look the same.
The good news is when you're really used
to these equations, they still
all look the same.
And that's because eventually, you'll
realize, it's all just expectimax
written out in various ways.
Sometimes there's a max when I'm acting
optimally, sometimes there's a
pi when I'm fixed to a policy.
And I can do anything I do for values
or Q values, because it's just a
matter of where I start my
recurrence in expectimax.
Do I start at a state, which evaluates
a state, or do I start at a Q state,
which evaluates an action?
So how do we solve an MDP?
If we know the MDP, we can solve it
offline without actually taking action
in the world, and we can compute
anything we want.
We can compute the optimal
values V star, optimal Q
values, optimal policies.
We can do that with value iteration,
or policy iteration,
which we also saw.
We can also evaluate any given fixed
policy, whether it's optimal or not,
and that was an algorithm called policy
evaluation, where you basically
compute what happens if you follow
this policy and not worry about
whether or not it's a good one.
For reinforcement learning,
we don't know the MDP.
And we saw last time two different ways
of dealing with the fact that
this critical quantity-- the transition
probabilities that tells us
what the actions do--
was missing.
So one thing we could do that we didn't
spend much time on, and we
won't come back to until much later in
the second part of this class, is we
could build a model.
We could try to figure out what the
transitions are by watching them.
Once we have approximate transitions,
we can then reduce it to
the known MDP case.
And while that's appealing, that's
not usually what people do.
Usually what people do is they take
what's called the Model-Free Approach.
And in t he Model-Free Approach, we can
still actually compute everything
of interest in a Markov
decision problem.
What we do is we look for all of the
averages and replace them with
samples, and that gives us analogs to
value iteration and policy evaluation.
The analog to the policy evaluation
was called value learning.
We saw that before.
And in that case, you basically just
watch some agent, possibly yourself,
execute the policy and figure out how
good it is based on observation.
What we're going to spend most of our
time on today is a very important
algorithm, the central logarithm for
reinforcement learning, really, called
Q learning, which enables you to compute
optimal qualities just by
watching the outcomes of your own
actions, even though you don't know
how to act optimally yet.
It's an amazing algorithm.
So for today, we're in the paradigm
of Model-Free Learning.
What's that mean?
Well, on the surface, we know it means
we're not actually going to compute a
model and then solve with
respect to that model.
But in practice what it means is that
your agent experiences the world as a
stream of what are called transitions
that form episodes.
So, for example, you start
in some state, s.
You take an action.
Forget for a second where that action
came from and how we knew to take it.
You receiver a reward r and then
you land in the state s prime.
From s prime, you take
action, a prime.
You receiver reward r prime and land
s double prime, and so on.
And so there's a stream of states and
actions and rewards that represents
your experience.
All of the Model-Free methods we are
going to talk about in this class,
though there are others, update
one transition at a time.
So every time you observe yourself going
from some state, s, taking an
action, a, and getting a reward and an
outcome, s, a, r, s prime, that's a
transition.
And every transition is going
to cause you to improve your
knowledge and do an update.
The design of these updates is so that
over time they will implement the
Bellman updates that we would have done
with a known MDP in an algorithm
like value iteration.
So most important algorithm and the one
we're going to build on today is
called Q-Learning.
And Q-Learning has some amazing
properties, but it took people a long
time to figure it out.
Essentially, people were held up for
decades in reinforcement learning
because they were staring at value
functions and trying to figure out how
to replace the value iteration update,
which starts with a max, with a
sampling process.
And we don't know how to sample maxes.
But then, the key breakthrough was that
what we should really do is not
be evaluating values, because
that's not really what we're
interested in any way.
We should be evaluating actions.
The value of an action is its Q value.
So here's how that works.
It's that same equation we've
seen over and over again.
In this case, this is
Q value iteration.
And so we get this equation, which says
if we knew the MDP, we would take
our Q values, which, in that algorithm,
would have been to a
certain depth, k.
We take them and we use them to compute
new Q values that are better.
Why are they better?
They're better because they have
an extra layer of expectimax.
And the way we do that is we write down
what expectimax would have done
for one layer if we started it,
evaluating action a from state s.
Well, what would it have done?
It would have had to average all the
outcomes, which we can't do in
reinforcement learning.
And then, for each outcome, s prime,
we would have added together the
instantaneous reward for that outcome
plus the discounted future, which
recurses into our current
approximation, Q sub k.
So here's Q value iteration.
It basically does the same thing as
value iteration, but it's shifted.
And what's cool about this is
essentially this update is an average.
Now, instead of having a max on the
outside, there's an average on the
outside, and we know how to
do averages and samples.
So here's how it goes in Q-Learning.
We're going to receive sample
transitions, so we're in some state,
s, we're in some action, a, we get a
reward, r, and we land in s prime.
And, of course, that reward and outcome
aren't the only possibility,
that's just what happened this time.
So what do we do?
Well we want to have the same idea of a
one-step look ahead, but we've only
got one sample.
We think, what can I conclude
about the Q state sa?
First of all, what is the Q state sa?
It's the value of action
a from the state.
So we're evaluating action a.
We just took action, a, and we received
a reward, r, and as far as we
can tell, to the best of our
approximation, the reward r we just
received is going to be followed in the
future by the maximum Q value for
the state s prime we land in.
Now why is it a maximum?
We assume that wherever we just landed,
we will now behave optimally.
So that maximum right there essentially
encodes optimal action in
the future in the right way.
So, according to this sample, it looks
like we are on track to receive r,
what we just received, plus our
discounted future estimate.
But then at the same time, we want to
average these samples together.
And the reason we want to average the
samples together is because this one
sample could be misleading.
It needs to kind of take its
place with all the others.
And so what we do is we keep
a running average.
And so this running average is going to
be constantly maintaining Q of sa,
and every time we get one of these
instantaneous one-step look ahead
samples, we're going to roll it into the
running average with weight alpha.
Alpha here is the learning rate.
The bigger alpha is, the more importance
we place on new samples,
which means we learn faster but less
stably, because we give a lot of
weight to each sample.
Now, Q-Learning is amazing.
The reason why Q-Learning is amazing
is you learn the optimal policy.
And you think, OK, fine.
We should have algorithms that
learn the optimal policy.
Q-Learning learns the optimal policy
even though you don't follow it.
So whereas value learning watched what
you did, and it said, well, it looks
like you're getting about 10
points from this state.
Well, that seems reasonable.
It doesn't seem like magic because of
course we can figure out how well our
algorithm is working for the policy
we're already following.
Q-Learning tells you how well you would
do optimally even though you're
messing up left and right.
This is what's called
Off-Policy Learning.
Let's take a look.
So what do we see here?
First of all, remember this is a table
of Q values, which means for each
state that has multiple actions, we
evaluate each action separately.
Because just because a state may
be good doesn't mean all of
its actions are good.
For example, you can see here that the
right thing to do is to walk straight
towards the plus 10, even though all of
the squares, in fact, on the cliff
have a bad action available.
You shouldn't take it.
You shouldn't jump off the cliff.
Now, of course, this agent jumps off
the cliff every now and then.
This agent is not following
the optimal policy.
In the optimal policy, you don't
occasionally jump off
the cliff for kicks.
But if you look at the Q Values, the
Q Value, for example, in this state
here, in the middle on the left--
the Q value to the right encodes what
you will receive under optimal action.
It doesn't encode what you would
receive given that you have a
propensity for jumping into the cliff.
And that's amazing.
It's not telling me how well I have
been doing, it tells me how
well I could do.
That's off-policy learning.
Even though you aren't following the
optimal policy, you still compute its
Q values, which means that any time I
could stop bumbling around and just do
the optimal thing once I've done
this process long enough to
have learned it.
A Couple other things to note.
First of all, I have no idea what this
square does because I can't get there.
Of course in reinforcement learning,
you're not going to learn about things
you can't try out.
Secondly, there's some stuff up here
that I have never really been in a
position to try.
So maybe they're great.
I don't know.
We'll talk about these
issues in a bit.
So for basic Q-Learning, what does
it required to accomplish
this off-policy magic?
It requires that you explore enough.
You have to try everything.
It also requires that you make the
learning rate small enough so that you
can construct a good average.
Of course, it can't decrease too
quickly, because once the learning
rate hits zero or close enough
to it, you stop learning.
In the limit, it doesn't matter how
you select actions, as long as you
basically try everything all the time.